I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
I was born a Saxon Lord,
but raised as a Dane
until the eve
of my sisters wedding,
when my family were murdered.
I am a warrior,
but when the Danes attacked
Alfred's stronghold
of Winchester,
all a man could do was run.
Some faster than others,
including my enemy, Young Odda.
And so Guthrum took Winchester.
Aethelwold pledged his
allegiance to the Danes.
Though Guthrum
still feared Alfred's God.
I could only hope that my now distant
wife and child would be safe.
We had no choice but to hide
and pray for a miracle.
Iseult, my virgin queen,
saved the King's son.
But at a cost
only she could see.
She gave Alfred strength.
With the King alive and well,
there is hope for Wessex.
Destiny is all.
Agreed, we have fired
a good number of ships.
-A fleet.
But in the meantime,
we have left hundreds of Danes
stranded in Wessex,
with no means of leaving--
Wulfhere I do not believe their
intention was to ever leave.
And in a few months there
will be more ships, more men.
Now is the time to fight.
To fight with what?
We are without an army;
and the Danes will
number thousands.
The men are out there,
Wulfhere, and they are waiting.
What they need is the call.
Indeed but... Lord...
What if I was to suggest
we escort you to Frankia--
That will not happen,
I will not hide.
Not here nor in Frankia.
-[Wulfhere] But my--
-I have prayed daily for guidance.
The only way I see to save
Wessex is with what we have begun;
one defining battle.
We shall be leaving the marshes.
Courage and faith.
-Amen.
Amen.
-Shh...
-[baby cries softly]
It will not be recorded that King
Alfred was a weak, frail man;
in mind, body and soul,
unfit to be called king.
Nothing of what you say is true.
But it would become true.
Never.
Now you, my love,
will remain here.
If I fail,
you must go to Frankia.
Not without you.
You must save
and protect our children.
For me, there can be
no other country but England,
no other wife but Aelswith.
Father Beocca.
Father... I am not saying
I know everything,
but the king
must continue to trust me.
The arrival of Asser
may change him.
The arrival of Brother Asser
has given him strength.
The Brother is not a warrior.
Now is a time for warriors.
And though I never thought I would
say it, we need Odda the Younger.
He commands the largest fyrd.
He is the beginning of our army,
that is where we are headed.
Uhtred I will do everything
I can to help.
I will be at your side.
I will be a flea
in Alfred's ear.
Thank you.
Your father would be
a proud man... as am I.
I shall ready my men and by
tomorrow I'll have horses waiting.
Uhtred...
You believe
the Danes can be defeated?
I will see you across the water,
Aelderman Wulfhere.
[sighs]
You will.
[indistinct chatter]
Aethelcod,
Aethelcod, my friend,
a man who would be
King of Wessex, thank you.
Thank you for coming to see me.
Certainly...
It is Aethelwold.
Yes, please.
Sit down. Sit down.
So... I want you to tell me
everything you know
about Alfred.
I have told you Lord,
he thinks with his dick.
[chuckles]
He can barely keep
his breeches on.
Hear the question, boy.
Not everybody enjoys a fool.
Alfred... though he may be
afflicted by pain,
he is as strong a man
as you will find.
He is also as clever a man
I was ready to have him as my advisor,
until he stole my crown.
His strength, Lord, I believe,
comes from his faith--
-[scoffs]
-[chuckles]
From God.
Do you believe in this God?
I believe in myself.
Why did Alfred steal the crown?
For silver, or to be
a stronger king to the people?
No! Um... Yes, in part.
Which is it?
Unfairly, I was not seen
as a man to follow... by some.
I was not a man to fight Danes,
it was said,
and which is true because
I know the Danes will win.
[chuckles]
Yes...
Where as... where as, Alfred...
Alfred believes that he can win.
-Even now?
-Yes!
Yeah, he is wrong,
of course, but... but his faith,
that God will not desert him,
will make him believe
that he will win.
Then you have to kill him.
I must kill him?
Who else... but King Aethelcod
can walk into Alfred's camp...
...and be welcomed as a friend?
[birds chirping]
Wulfhere and his men.
[gasps]
[mumbles]
Stay away! I have skills!
Put that piece of tin
away, boy.
Oh, thank Christ
you are English.
I thought you were one of them,
what with the hair.
Where is the Aelderman Wulfhere?
Gone, Lord.
I am Halig.
I take care of the horses.
Gone where?
Now I'm thinking on it, Lord,
he did not say.
-I thought you would know.
-Wulfhere, where is he?
-He has gone, Lord.
-Lord.
-He has gone where?
-He didn't say.
-He has left you horses, Lord.
-We keep moving.
Without Wulfhere?
Our plan doesn't change.
We make our way
to Odda's estate.
We cannot use the Roman roads.
We can make our way to my
farmstead and from there across
-covered ground to Odda's.
-And that is the safest path, Leofric?
It is, Lord.
Let's return to the others.
There is pain here
for you, my love.
-Do you know them?
-Tenants.
[chickens clucking]
No...
[shuddering]
[sobs]
[dialogue muted
over soundtrack music]
[sobbing]
No... No...
We shall bury the dead...
and pray for their souls.
When you are ready...
I would like to say a prayer,
for Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
I must search for Mildrith,
she may be dead and unburied.
Uhtred no, no...
She has buried
your son with care,
and she has left this place.
It was no longer
home for her anymore.
Believe me.
Your tears on the Earth will
show him that you loved him.
[sobbing]
Lord, may I ask
what you are writing?
The first of many letters,
each will say the same:
"The men of Wessex and beyond
shall gather at Egbert's Stone,
and together we will fight."
[Beocca] When you send out
your messengers Lord,
might I suggest you hand
them the letters personally,
perhaps place your hand
on their shoulder.
It will embolden them,
I'm sure.
Thank you, Beocca,
I will do that.
You know I did this to you;
when I saved the king's son.
You did not.
[crying]
I knew, an innocent would die...
I'm tired of being like this.
I have seen too much.
I know too much.
I want to see no more.
[Odda the Elder]
Mildrith?!
Lord, you should be resting,
we should all be resting.
I am tired of resting, I spend
too many days doing nothing.
Then at least sit,
before you become unsteady.
-Where is my wife?
-She is resting, Lord.
-My son?
-He is away, Lord.
Still?
Important business demands time.
It is not a betrayal...
No, it is not, Lord.
Look what I have
done to you, child.
-I am content enough, Lord.
-Look what God has done to you.
You deserve so much more
than the clothes of a nun.
I have purpose, Lord.
My child is with God,
and I am close to God.
There is joy in my days,
at times.
Do not fear the Danes.
you will be protected.
My son will ensure that.
You are Earl Skorpa?
You are here to surrender
and not waste my time?
I am here to negotiate.
[Skorpa]
Surrender and you will live,
talk too much
and I will kill you.
Of all the Aeldermen of Wessex,
I am the man who can assemble
the greatest fyrd,
the greatest army.
I now have
to make a choice.
Whether to side with Guthrum,
or with Skorpa.
One Dane looks much like
the other to me.
I am occupying your land;
why should I not
simply crush you?
Accept my invitation.
Eat with myself
and with my father,
and I will tell you
all about my land;
the range of my influence.
I am sure an agreement
can be reached,
neither of us need lose any men,
neither of us need be weakened.
-Eat?
-And drink, at my hall.
I assure you this is no trap.
I will arrive at your hall
after the new moon.
I shall expect you.
Then we have peace,
at least for a time?
Oh, we do.
You have lost much:
fathers, mothers...
...a son... lovers...
I have you...
I have a brother...
-Ragnar.
-Yes.
Your sister, Thyra...
Yes?
She is alive?
[sighs softly]
No she's dead in the fire.
Uhtred she lives
and is being held in the north.
It is the truth.
Skorpa told me.
I thought at first it could be
a lie to torment you.
Hearing it from me
would have made it true,
but now I know
that it is true. She lives.
You've seen it?
Yes. I've seen her...
...but I will see her no more,
the gift is fading.
When this battle is done,
Uhtred, your path leads north.
It will be time
to face your past.
And you'll be with me?
Always.
Lord... If God's help
is required,
how could he look favorably
upon Uhtred, a non-believer.
God is good.
Yes, Lord, but in
following the heathen,
what does that
say of our beliefs?
Death could be waiting over
the very next hill
and it will be Uhtred
who stands in its way.
I have no doubt, a Dane will
always protect his plunder.
The king is of value.
He is here to protect the king.
Something neither
you nor I could do.
He is a man without a soul.
Then I shall be his soul, Lord.
I shall pray for him.
I will ride beside him,
always and into battle.
I will be his conduit to God.
And if you fall, in battle?
With the help
of your prayers, brother,
I shall become
invincible I'm sure.
Brother Asser....
I should like you to be
the first of my messengers.
[horse whinnies]
Morning.
Sleep well?
He means did you hump well?
-I know what he means.
-Sleep well lady?
[Alfred]
If I may speak... to you all.
Though we are yet to complete
the first segment of our journey
to Odda's estate, it is
important we begin the second.
Word of our army's gathering
point must be despatched
to the further reaches
of our land.
Brother Asser here
will be my first messenger.
Halig.
Yes, Lord.
You will also be my voice.
I will, Lord.
And me, Lord.
Hild?
Lord, she is a woman.
I am as good a horseman
as anyone here.
If it means more Danes
will die then I'll do it.
Yes, Hild... you will.
Your horses... belong to whom?
The Lord Odda.
-You will let us pass?
-Are you selling or buying?
Selling to the Danes.
There is a peace.
Did you not know?
That Odda has made a peace,
no, I did not.
Odda is loyal. We shall see
for ourselves what is true.
[snickers]
Lord, you should remain
out of sight
until we can be sure
of your safety.
Odda is not a danger.
But who sits with Odda?
I will not hide.
[Beocca]
Lord, please, hear the advice.
You are a symbol of Wessex,
you are the standard around
which our army will gather.
You cannot be put at risk.
Very well.
I must see this
with my own eyes.
-Lord, that is not advisable.
-I have made up my mind!
If there is treachery,
it is something I must witness.
-Then I will go with you.
-I do not require a nursemaid!
-I am a priest.
-And I a King!
You will wait here with Iseult.
I am aware of the care
I need to take.
[indistinct chatter]
Nuns should not be so pretty nor
have lips that demand to be kissed.
I see you agree.
-When is it you are leaving?
-When I am rested, Lord.
Lord...
[whispers indistinct]
[Odda the Elder] What is it?
Have the Danes arrived?
Leofric, he is outside.
Then bring him inside,
he is our man.
He is with Uhtred.
Bring them both to me.
[indistinct chatter]
Leofric, Uhtred!
My prayers have been answered!
God is good.
Lords...
It is good to see you
both safe and well.
Leofric, you are home.
Where in God's name
have you been?
Hiding, Lord,
and killing Danes.
Hopefully, not on my land.
[Uhtred]
We have been sent by the king.
We bring orders from the king.
-What king is that?
-King Alfred?
Who else, Lord?
[Odda the Younger] Wessex,
it seems, is full of kings.
There is Guthrum, who is
the King of East Anglia,
who now sits in Winchester.
There is Aethelwold here,
who will tell anyone who cares
to listen that he is king,
where will it end?
-I have Alfred's written order.
-It means nothing.
-You are to raise the fyrd.
-It is over for Alfred!
Alfred gave up on Wessex.
He decided to save himself!
No man has been more loyal
to Alfred than my father and I,
but he has failed us.
Danes surround us
and he is hiding!
Alfred, is king of the eels,
slippery and elusive.
I see it's true...
...you have
sided with the Danes.
What has Skorpa promised you?
Are you to be king, Odda?
-Leofric, are you are still my man?
-Am I right?
I asked you a question, Leofric?
I am still your man, Lord.
Then you will finish the business you
have with this Dane and kill him.
You have my order. Kill him.
Lord, I cannot do that.
I stand here
as Alfred's messenger.
[Odda the Younger] I will not
tell you again, Leofric.
[Uhtred]
Should any man try to kill me,
then that man
is a traitor to the king.
Leofric, you will kill him!
Alfred is no longer my king!
[Leofric]
I will not do it, Lord!
-My son--
-Father, you will not interfere.
[gasps]
May your mother forgive me.
And may you be
forgiven for your treason.
[all murmuring]
Lord, forgive him,
let him die a noble.
Forgive him...
I ask you this as your servant.
Odda...
you will do as I command;
you will raise
the Somerset fyrd.
Lord, forgive my son, please!
I will not forgive
what I have seen.
You will raise the fyrd!
[sighs]
Yes, Lord.
I will need 20 horsemen...
to take word
to all men able to carry sword,
hook or spear.
The word is that
Alfred is king...
[all yelling]
...and will fight alongside
the swords of Wessex
to his dying breath!
-Come on!
-[all cheering]
Come on! Come on!
May we speak?
About our son.
You know?
Then there is
nothing left to say.
I am sorry that his death
was something that
you had to face alone.
[scoffs]
I was not alone.
Being without a husband
does not mean I am alone.
Then I am sorry for the life
that I have given you.
I have found peace,
I hope you can do the same.
Was there sickness?
-I would like to understand.
-Children are frail.
And you will have other sons,
I'm sure, with your queen.
Is she here?
Yes.
I would like you
to leave me alone,
never speak to me again.
We have nothing
that binds us, nothing.
Avoid me, please.
Uhtred Ragnarson,
should I be pleased to see you?
Skorpa of the White Horse.
I am expected,
by the Lord Odda.
The Lord Odda is in the ground,
buried as a traitor.
So what now,
do I speak with you;
does the truce stand?
For today it stands,
tomorrow we will kill you.
You will kill me... with what?
I have almost
1,000 men to call upon.
Your ships have been burned,
Skorpa, by Alfred.
He is gathering
a great Saxon army.
I am aware my ships are gone,
and I will have my revenge.
You should return to Guthrum
and prepare to die!
Did your queen tell you
that your sister
is being humped in the arse each
and every night by one-eyed Sven?
Did your mother tell you that she
should have kept her legs closed?
I will look for you
first across the battle field.
I will be there, and I will
not be difficult to find.
[Alfred]
He will go to Guthrum?
I believe he will, Lord.
Then the battle
is one step nearer.
Beocca,
you should wash out your mouth.
Yes, Lord, I will... with ale.
How many men?
Four hundred. No more.
And this is
the great Saxon army?
Their numbers will grow.
We need to march.
There needs to be a
story of a slaughter.
Only days ago Ragnar
was asking if the war was over?
Skorpa is right,
there must be a slaughter.
We must take the fight
to Alfred and his God.
And you are ready
to kill your brother?
If it comes to that, yes.
Then we shall face
one great army with another.
[Alfred]
Once the armies are assembled,
I shall speak to them, as one.
Each man should know...
...this war
is not only about land....
Should the heathens win,
then Christ is defeated.
[Uhtred] When you speak to the men,
Lord, you cannot make it a sermon.
Then what do you suggest I say?
Tell them that you will
die for them, that's good.
Tell them that we will make
the Danes pay in blood,
and that they will be
rewarded in plunder.
I am to talk of revenge
and greed?
They are men, Lord,
not angels.
We shall stop for a moment.
Halt... We halt!
Lord?
It is Egbert's Stone.
Within these next few yards,
we will know if
we have an army,
of angels or otherwise.
I will go alone.
If no one is there, what then?
I see...
Not a single one.
Not a single man
has answered my call.
Then we wait.
We must wait, Lord.
A fine knife...
A Dane's knife.
This thing?
Yes, I took it from a Dane,
a Dane I killed.
-Where?
-Winchester.
This was before you groveled
on your arse to Guthrum?
Before I presented
myself to him, yes.
I was not, however,
treated in a kingly manner
and decided to escape.
A king under the Danes
is no king.
Uhtred, I do like you, but I rather tire
of your preaching.
Have you ever thought of
becoming a priest?
-Ever since I was a boy.
-That is a lie.
I baptized him twice,
he's still not a Christian.
[knife cuts]
For luck.
Then I will need
a lock from you.
Where is Alfred?
Watching...
waiting for his army.
I think I shall go
and sit with him a while.
You are fond of him now?
For luck.
[breathing heavily]
Lord...
I thought
you would like company.
What do you see?
What do you hear?
-I hear nothing, Lord.
-No... No...
There is a change
in the shadows, in the air.
They are out there.
I see nothing but grass, Lord.
-Beyond the grass, trees.
-There! There!
It's men.
And more... more men there.
They have answered the call.
The swords of England,
they're coming.
[chuckles]
It's the swords of Wessex!
Swords of England!
Today, is a day for warriors.
A day to kill your enemies.
A day we make the Pagans wish
they had never heard of Wessex!
Today, we fight for Wessex!
[all cheering]
[Alfred]
And not only for Wessex.
We have men here from
Northumbria,
from Mercia, from East Anglia.
And why are the Pagan's here?
They want your wives
for their pleasure.
They want your children
as their slaves.
They want your homes
as their own!
But they do... not...
know us!
[all cheering]
They do not know our swords,
they do not know our axes,
our spears,
they do not know our courage!
And today... We kill them!
[all cheering]
We shall make the ground
red with their blood!
We shall strip them
of what they have plundered,
we shall make them
cry out for mercy,
and there will be none!
No mercy!
[all chanting]
No mercy! No mercy! No mercy!
[chanting continues]
Should I fall,
you and Hild are to take my
horse and ride clear of here.
You will not fall,
I forbid it.
Everything I have is packed
in my bags, it's yours.
You will not fail.
I fight for you.
[chanting continues]
Kill them all!
Then no mercy it must be.
Should you meet Uhtred
in battle there can be no doubt.
No mercy.
None.
We should not be
holding back, Lord.
We should attack
with every man.
I will decide how we fight.
You will follow my orders.
Yes, Lord.
No mercy.
Form our lines.
Form our lines!
Shields up!
-Advance!
-[Leofric] Come on!
Forward.
Hold the line, we work as one.
We do not break.
Shields, lock.
Hold the line.
-Halt!
Wulfhere, I will have your guts
you traitorous bastard!
This is our land!
[all cheering]
[commanding orders indistinct]
First in line, as you wished.
[all yelling]
Here they come!
Hold!
[all grunting]
[screaming in pain]
Keep the wall tight!
[Leofric]
Have that Wulfhere, you bastard!
Hold!
Leofric!
[speaks indistinct]
Leave him! Leave him!
Close the gaps!
Keep the wall tight!
Advance!
Three, two, one...
[all grunting in unison]
No mercy!
[yells]
No more ground shall be lost!
Follow me!
[screaming]
God have mercy!
[horse whinnying]
[people screaming]
We fall back! As one!
We ease!
[all chanting in unison]
Hold! We hold here!
We go no further!
Edge backwards with me
at my level!
[screaming]
[all grunting in unison]
Uhtred Ragnarson!
Can you hear me?
I hear you, Skorpa.
Do you wish to surrender?
I have a gift for you!
Your queen!
-No mercy!
-[all yelling]
You will be struck down
with my spear!
[screaming]
And you will spend eternity
in the fires of hell!
Uhtred!
[grunts]
Take the horse.
[groans in pain]
Lord, what are your orders?
Lord?
Did you see that?
It came as the priest said.
What, Lord?
Their God is with them.
So what are your orders?
[mumbles indistinct]
[yells indistinct]
No mercy!
His grave is to be marked
like that of an Aelderman.
I shall see to it.
[Beocca]
Uhtred...
Iseult is whole.
She has been wrapped
and made ready for burial.
[Uhtred sighs deeply]
I want her to have a pyre.
Then she shall have it.
Uhtred...
for all that you have done...
...all that you have shown me,
thank you.
You have given everything.
You are the man
I always hoped you would become.
[exhales]
[Uhtred]
In the year 878, at Ethandun,
King Alfred
defeated Guthrum of the Danes
and drove them from Wessex.
I am indebted,
Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
Wessex is indebted.
There can be no negotiation,
Lord, only surrender.
-That is your advice?
-It is.
I hear you.
Lord.
[Uhtred] Peace was secured
with hostages,
including my friend Brida...
and my brother Young Ragnar.
Peace was further secured
by Earl Guthrum's baptism
and acceptance
of the Christian God.
Do you renounce the Devil
and all his work?
-I do.
-Let this water cleanse you
and make you worthy
of God's blessing.
Guthrum, you are now
a child of God.
[all]
Amen.
[Uhtred]
As for Uhtred the Godless...
...my journey continues.
My path leads north,
to blood feuds, to revenge.
And to Bebbanburg.
Destiny is all.